this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size we're
moving infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials and an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/ SC radio hello and welcome to software
engineering radio this is Travis Kimmel
and today I have Laura Hogan and deep hi
super money I'm joining me on the show
previously deep OLED product and design
and Kickstarter Hillary for America
charity water and Adobe and Laura was
the VP of engineering at Kickstarter and
engineering director at Etsy the two of
since partner to co-found wherewithall
where they help other leaders build
mentor and grow their products and
engineering organizations deep on lara
thank you for joining me on software
engineering radio thank you so much
thanks for happy to be here yeah fun
stuff to talk about today we'll be
talking about revitalizing crops
functional product engineering and
design organizations of any size and
specifically we're going to cover a
number of different levers that leaders
can pull it will ultimately help their
team ship higher quality software faster
so first let's start with a little
clarification when we talk about helping
organizations reach their potential what
does that really mean yeah so we work
with a variety of different
organizations they can be any team that
has some sort of product or engineering
component so it can be small seed
startups growth stage startups larger
companies nonprofits you know all
anything that sort of encompasses
anything with product and engineering
and what we really love to do is to
partner with leaders emerging leaders
individuals on teams to make sure that
these product in
engineering organizations know how to
create and execute their vision how to
grow and nurture leaders and essentially
build teams that can collaborate and
coordinate in this weird delicate little
dance that is product development so we
love partnering closely with leaders to
help coach them and help them make sure
that they understand exactly what they
need to do to build foundational skills
and lead their team successfully and
confidently we do a lot of things around
auditing product driven development
processes making sure that we do
workshops and roundtables and trainings
to help cross-functional teams like
product and design and engineering teams
know exactly what they have to do
between setting a strategy creating a
roadmap and executing on that roadmap so
both Laura and I just really love how
much energy it takes to collaborate and
coordinate in a really healthy and
impactful fashion and we want to bring
those learnings into product and
engineering organizations that we work
with it's so much fun awesome
yeah and what's the composition of a
typical team you might engage with oh
good question it's kind of all over the
place yeah generally there's you know
gonna be some engineering leadership
involved bringing us in to help sort of
look at their engineering team make sure
that they can scale make sure that they
can you know as they grow may be
excellent engineers are now being
promoted into management positions or
maybe the engineering team has sort of
doubled in size or acquired a new
company and grown and we also work a lot
with product and design teams as well so
you have product leaders who are setting
a strategy and trying to execute on
their North Star vision and they need to
make sure that coordination across
engineering product design data science
research all the different related teams
is sort of happening in a positive
healthy and high-velocity way so we
focus a lot on what might be holding
back that kind of strategic execution
yeah I also one of the things that I
like about this new role that we've kind
of created for ourselves is we get to
work with people up and down the
hierarchy like sometimes you know I'm
interacting a ton with senior leaders
the executive team other times I'm
really on the ground coaching line
managers are people who are brand new to
management and that's one of the best
things as you know all of those
different levels are necessary
to be thinking about and like nurturing
the health of this you know product
engineering design organization totally
so sometimes you know say a VP of
engineering or a CTO might bring in
Laura to kind of work with the
engineering team and then as she sort of
gets the lay of the land she might
notice that there are improvements or
things that need to be improved on the
product and design side so she might
bring me in or vice versa so sometimes
we work with clients together sometimes
we actually oftentimes we go in
individually and then what's amazing is
both of us kind of have these realms
that were really good at working in so
we can bring in the other person and
almost tag-team with them to kind of
improve an entire organization in one
fell swoop
have you when you're working with how do
they typically just try to describe
their goals oh yeah so often so when I
get called in usually it's an executive
or a really senior leader usually within
the engineering team although not always
will be like I like I smell something's
weird I don't know what it is yes
they'll start to it's you know um we
were just talking in an event last night
and we started to talk about some of you
it's like organizational health smells
like there's like a rumor mill and
you're not sure why there's a rumour
mill why does this you know
misinformation being spread or people
are leaving in you're not sure if that's
a good or a bad thing you know there's
all these kind of different smells and
so usually we get brought in because
someone's like I needed some help or you
just like come in and see if you think
you think that this is weird - and often
especially when we're each working with
individuals like when I'm coaching
someone all that stuff is confidential
so I try to you know create the safe
space for any individual that I'm
working with to really be honest because
I don't work at this company they don't
have to worry about what I think of them
or or their role or you know what
they're gonna to say and usually I can
get a little bit more information about
the shape of whatever the thing is
that's going wrong and again I that only
it's remain confidential so people can
feel safe but sure after collecting lots
of information I can usually try to
propose workshops trainings I offer
group coaching called roundtables or
bringing in someone like depo who can
really talk about tactics and processes
and you know more like infrastructural
stuff too
yeah on the product and design side I
think folks reach out because they're
like you know we're a shipping product
but we think we could be shipping a lot
better or a lot faster or products that
have a stronger impact on the business
or you know better solve customer
problems so it's sort of exactly what
Laura was saying there's like a smell
that feels a little off and they just
want some external opinion to come in
and check it out and generally you come
in you do some exploratory calls and
conversations coaching you know auditing
maybe how they set their strategy and
coordinator cross teams and very quickly
you start diagnosing what's holding back
the team or the individuals from kind of
being their best selves and so we start
putting in place talks or workshops or
roundtables to start chipping away at
that and leveling up all the teams I
love this idea of org smells do you have
a sort of a top three structurally or
something like that that you see over
and over yeah we were chatting about
this last night at this talk that we
gave here in New Zealand and I think
like Laura mentioned the rumor mill
might be churning high people might be
at Rhydding maybe at a at a pace that
leadership isn't quite comfortable with
I'm not always a bad sign but it's
definitely something to investigate
maybe folks on the product and
engineering teams are not referring
people to work within the organization
you know bringing in their own network
to work there that always makes me kind
of question it people are really happy
and enjoying their jobs and feel like
it's a healthy environment they want to
bring in their friends their network to
work there as well so those are some of
the things to keep an eye out for right
and yet another one that I just thought
of two is a prime when product either
hasn't shipped anything in a while or
that the team has it shipped anything in
a while or people keep on starting and
then throwing out projects that's
usually a good smell and do you see
these things typically arise is this
sort of like a punctuated equilibrium
like I know where it reaches a certain
size and they go through another wave of
this or when do organizations run into
this stuff that's a good question
yeah I think there's like inflection
points where this can happen in a more
like can be more common and I think
Laura mentioned a few of them early on
so maybe you're except
general individual contributors are now
being promoted into management positions
so what were some of your great
engineers your great PM's and designers
are now themselves running engineering
teams product teams design teams so
that's an in front plan awesome like
management it's just not it doesn't
there's some overlapping skills but yeah
it's a whole different discipline yeah
it's a whole different way of coaching
them to now be successful in their new
roles other inflection points are maybe
the company has like exponentially grown
like doubled in size in a short amount
of time or you know 30 new people have
joined in in two months sometimes it can
be when the competitive landscape
changes you know suddenly someone you
didn't have a lot of competition or you
thought you truly understood your market
and had found your product market fit
and now things were changing and you
start realizing oh we need to innovate
into a different space and maybe you
have a Netflix that muscle in a while
and and you need some help to kind of
get that going it could also be some you
know acquisitions can be really change
induced times you're you've acquired a
company you've been acquired maybe you
want to bring in some outside help to
help guide that transition properly and
make sure you're maintaining healthy
velocity shipping great product and
maintaining a healthy culture I want
also honestly like leadership changes
are the probably the one that I think of
that most like I you know a company may
not be changing size they may not have
been acquired there bro BAPS been you
know set in stone for a while but you
get a leadership change that really just
shakes things up in a good or bad way I
yeah I think about that all the time
that's often actually the ones that I'm
talking about that's totally my bias
good so what were some of the levers
that leaders can pull to better support
their ORS maybe if you have you know
sort of a top five and then we can dig
into them one at a time oh yeah I mean
there's so many okay I'll start talking
about one clarifying roles and
responsibilities tends to be the thing
that structurally can create a lot of
change throughout an organization so as
an organization kind of starts up you
normally don't have like a career ladder
or a skills matrix or you know really
well you often have to find people who
are doing lots and lots of you know
different things wearing lots of
different hats and then these you add
more people or you grow the company
often it's really hard it is English
between what someone wants to do once
what someone should be doing and what
someone is doing but doesn't really want
to be doing especially if you want to be
promoting people and recognizing their
own growth or you want to be giving them
more responsibility
usually clarifying roles of
responsibilities with things again like
a career ladder or a skills matrix or
just I like to talk a lot about this
Venn diagram of like if you've got you
know three leads on a featured team a
engineering lead an engineering manager
and a product manager how can you
articulate what those people are each
supposed to be responsible for and where
they have overlaps and responsibilities
so if you draw this Venn diagram with
these three circles hopefully it can be
a tool to help those three peer leaders
decide who's doing what who people can
go to ask questions over what kinds of
responsibilities and what stuff is you
know overlapping what should be shared
responsibilities and make that you know
get that it documented somewhere is that
there can be a shared understanding that
can evolve over time and what's the
what's sort of the happy stay here is
this sort of driving towards kind of
discrete ownership or does it look like
when what does clarity look like clarity
I'm gonna put a stake in the ground and
say the good stuff happens when there's
a shared understanding and actually from
my point of view it doesn't even matter
who's doing what you can come up with
totally bananas other titles and then
those three standard ones and be like
you know what but you're responsible for
a I'm responsible for being and this
other person is responsible for see and
like as long as there's that shared that
genuinely shared understanding not just
with those three people or however many
people but with the entire team that
needs to work with them and rely on them
that is like the holy grail of
clarification of roles and
responsibilities yeah and I think when
you've achieved that what you see is
better accountability across teams you
see expectations that are being met and
that people really understand so matched
expectations and in general you see
higher velocity so you see people
producing better higher-quality output
in pursuit of whatever the
organization's goals are I'd love to dig
in on that accountability a little bit
you feel like that can be such a
lightning rod
for builders right for people whether
it's design whether it's product-moment
engineering what's a healthy way to
think about accountability and you know
a non-trivial size to work yeah I mean I
think almost it's like what is what it
what do things look like when there is
not accountability and that's where you
can all be you know I think if you don't
have that clarity that Laura's been
talking about the way that manifests is
poor accountability and that might mean
they're sort of inertia right nothing is
happening with any sort of urgency
within the teams there might be sort of
controlled chaos like maybe too much is
happening but it actually doesn't have a
lot of impact or maybe everyone's
checked out and feeling sort of
ambivalent and so that's why if you
you've got to sort of check into why
that might be happening nine times out
of ten the diagnosis that we've come up
with when we start experiencing that and
seeing that on the teams that we're
leaving it's that folks don't understand
what they're responsible for and they
want that clarity right Laura talks so
much about how brains need that clarity
so that they can feel comforted and safe
am I getting that right all right yeah
totally thanks Deepa
and so that clarity is so important
because once someone truly understands
what is their individual
responsibilities in their role as a
product manager a designer a tech lead a
DevOps engineer you know any of those
roles what are their individual
responsibilities and what are their
shared responsibilities within their
team and cross functionally they can
start delivering on that and then
they're there being more accountable so
when they say that they can do something
they're able to do it they're able to do
it in a safe secure an easier way and so
then everything just sort of gets better
and that train just feels like it's
flying right off the tracks in a good
way
I been giggling this whole time because
I've been I've been thinking about this
word accountability and it's just it can
be so meaningless of a word but we all
might have used it it's so important to
like it you know I can't abilities
necessary for us to each you know be
able to work with with other people and
be humans to each other but like it's
actually when people ask me about
accountability you know when a CTO it's
like how can I hold people accountable
that is a smell I mean what I usually
have coaching questions like kimmykak
can it give me a for instance or like
what is the kind of building
to you like what are we actually talking
about here because people don't show up
to do a bad job mostly probably don't
work with so see you man so like when
your ass came to hold people accountable
like what is it that you actually really
mean are you talking about
how do we measure impact how do you
measure success are you talking about
how to make sure you can penalize
someone when they mess up like are we
are we talking about post-mortems act
like what are we what on earth I mean so
I'm over here giggling cuz I don't have
a real answer yet but what defo just
mentioned is is usually where I try to
talk about if like humans have these six
core needs at work one of them is like
certainty and predictability one of them
is understanding how their work and
their job as you know contributing to
improvement progress either of the
company or the organization as a whole
or of their team of or of their own
improvement or progress in their careers
people want to understand how they
belong to a group people want to
understand where their status is in this
group people want to feel like things
are being equal and fair and so all of
these core needs tell me accountability
isn't really what we're talking about
we're talking about something else and
I'm never everyone kind of has a
different reason why I've asked this
questions so Travis why did you ask that
question
I mean I've certainly been on
engineering teams where the
accountability word comes up and what I
translate that my head into is like who
do I lack yeah like that space that
accountability you know belongs to so I
guess we you know an interesting
question here's what's a better
headspace than that let's say you're
talking to someone who's coming from
this who do I thump because I'm mad
nothing's getting done headspace that's
a smell where do we want them to be
coming from I mean I want that leader to
take responsibility for the fact that
their people don't have clarity like if
and maybe getting a little curious about
why like why do they feel the need to to
block someone you know where is that
coming from is it really about that
person or is there something else
happening some missed expectation that
they have that isn't happening and then
you have to almost go on this
fact-finding mission Laura calls a data
gathering you sort of figure out what
exactly is happening that's making you
you know feel like it's accountability
that's not being like the accountability
is not happening it could be something
else but you it's almost onus is
you as a leader to go root that out yeah
and to make sure that you've done due
diligence of making sure you've set
clear expectations like if someone's not
doing their job it's probably because
the leadership didn't actually make sure
that there was that shared understanding
of who's doing what and what our goals
are and how we're measuring it like it's
I mean absolutely there will absolutely
be times when people don't meet
expectations but you can't
swak them and hopefully you won't ever
but like you can't even have a
conversation and which feedback can
happen until you clarify those
expectations and make sure that there's
this shared understanding of what you're
expecting of other people I mean it
almost sounds like you're suggesting and
maybe I'm going too far with this one
but the right answer if you're in
leadership for who who's accountable for
this is sort of like me it's yourself
yeah yes I mean what kind of stops with
you it's you and and your leadership
team working together and constantly you
know it takes work to create a healthy
clear shared environment where people
want to do their best work
I mean it's Laura said we most likely
don't work with sociopaths everyone's
showing up every day wanting to do their
best but do they have the framework and
the guardrails in place to do that best
work so let's imagine that I am someone
who you know needs more accountability
on the team and you're helping me
reframe that headspace
we're like the top three nuts and bolts
let's do this next week things you could
recommend I think the first thing is I
would talk about observations of
behaviors and then the impact of those
behaviors and Travis you know I've
talked about this a little bit before
but in terms of like okay when we're
talking about accountability what
specifically paint me a picture of what
it is that you want to see people doing
sometimes that means you know I'll ask
Alito what was it was a behavior that
you want to see in terms of
accountability and they'll say I want
this person to email me a report of time
spent on the project and how far it's
come or how much more money we've made
this week or whatever it is and I'm like
cool ask them to do that you know don't
you see what I need you to be
accountable for this it's like no you
clearly have a picture in your head of
what of how you want them to behave and
then also I usually ask what's the
impact of them sending you that report
you know what's the impact of whatever
behavior you've just described and often
they'll say something like oh that I
won't feel like I'm in the dark
I'm like right this is about you and
your knee it's this isn't about what
this other person doing for a job and
it's not always the same reason
obviously but usually that impact is
awesome really illustrative of what this
leader is going through and what their
biggest fear is right now because again
it's all about this leaders deal it's
rarely about someone intentionally or or
just you know mistakenly doing a bad job
right well another thing that I think
that teams and leaders can make sure are
put in place is that sometimes what
manifests is lack of accountability like
in that example that Laura was sharing
where the leader wasn't getting the
transparency that they needed into the
day-to-day of a project or status or
understanding if a ship date was going
to get met sometimes that results
because of communication breakdowns and
so when people feel like someone's not
being accountable they're not doing what
I was expected of them it could be
because they are actually doing that but
there's no paper trail there's no flow
of communication in order to share that
information and almost make that
information self-serve so you're not
having to ask people for things but you
can go see the state of a project what
phase a product and the development
lifecycle is you know how to maybe go to
a particular meeting or pop into a slack
channel in order to give your feedback
or some about something or share an
insight that you learned on a sales call
or something like that and so something
that I think a lot of companies don't do
well enough especially as companies have
more and more remote teams and you know
are more distributed in nature is
creating the documents the meetings and
calling out the milestones that kind of
keep the product development train on
track so when people complain to me
about accountability sometimes I feel
like what that what they want happening
is actually happening but they're just
not aware of it and so you need to make
sure that you have sort of living
product documents living processes that
make it easy to get that information
when you need it in order for you to
coordinate in order for other teams to
coordinate and so that can actually
really boost accountability so Jeff
definitely I work a lot with teams to
make sure that they're checking in on
what are their product development
processes and making sure that that's
well documented really integral
documents like roadmaps are up to date
always
they're living as in they you know never
go stale and other people can reliably
make plans against that awesome I think
this is a great place to dig in so
living product documents and processes
what does that actually mean was was a
living part yeah I mean um you know by
living what I'm trying to do is I'm
trying to call attention to the fact
that your product development processes
your key product documents like your
strategic objectives and your roadmaps
these are documents and processes that
need to be tended to they need to be
updated regularly especially as the
organization might grow might add on
more remote team members so on and so
forth because if you don't take the time
to document your product processes
basically individual teams end up
reinventing the wheel duplicating
efforts or they have unnecessary and
wasteful disagreement and so a lot of
time companies don't spend enough time
really explicitly calling out what their
product development lifecycle is and
where these critical documents that keep
that product development train on the
tracks live and so when I talk about
product developing processes I'm really
talking about critical documents like
roadmaps strategic plans a whole
historical archive of experiments ran or
a way to go see what a feature or
product that was launched how it
performed you know where can I go get in
a self-serve manner sort of an
assessment of the impact of feature X or
product Y and additionally you need to
think about the meetings that almost
anchor the development workflow as you
start off doing some discovery and then
you move into design and research and
then you develop the the product and
then go ahead and get ready to test and
release it and then afterwards once
you've released it how are you cycling
back to check in on how it's performing
and decide what to do next there are a
few critical meetings that can really
keep that sort of flowing smoothly and
making sure everyone has access to all
the information they need not just the
team building the product but leadership
and stakeholders and lastly I like to
use milestones to make sure you know
it's kind of clear it's sort of the
little bit of a shared rallying cry that
whenever you hear these milestones
announced you sort of know where the
project is in the state
okay look discovery is complete a design
is complete we've just started coding
and now we hit code complete and we've
tested it and it's test complete now it
shipped these are critical milestones
that you kind of want to share super
broadly within the organization not just
within the product team but with the
marketing team the sales team the BD
team so that everyone knows the state of
projects and can you I feel like there's
a lot of confusion in the industry
sometimes around what a product roadmap
looks like in an agile world oh my gosh
totally it's this fear that we're gonna
slip back into you know the waterfall
days of your have you what does that
yeah yeah such a great question and it's
such a it's like a hot topic right now
right I kind of get a little bummed when
people talk about roadmaps but what
they're actually talking about our
project plans or Gantt charts you know
they want to know the size of the scope
and the due date and who's working on it
that's not really a road map a road map
comes out of the strategy for your
product for your company for your
feature team the key inputs into a
strategy or obviously some sort of
mission and vision
what is that future North Star and then
you break that mission and vision down
into strategic objectives and measurable
goals so now you have the inputs into
actually creating your roadmap I like my
roadmaps to actually be essentially a
queue of problems that you're gonna
focus on problem statements so my
roadmaps never have project names or
never have you know the solution like
onboarding v2 instead my roadmap is a
list of the problem statements that the
team thinks is valuable to focus on and
to solve those problems will result in
customer impact and positive business
impact
so my roadmap might look like improving
attrition and the publishing flow or
making sure users are set up for success
when starting their new project or
something like that so state them as
problems and not try to avoid trying to
slide your roadmap into what is actually
more of a project plan or a project
management document that that lists out
sort of the the scheduling and the
resourcing of a project Ravin DB is a
multi master distributed database with
no single point of failure multiple
nodes can accept both read and write
requests your database cluster giving
your users 24/7 availability a fully
transactional non-relational database
Ravin DB offers acid throughout the
cluster secure your organization with
backups in real time keep everything
running with assignment failover if a
node goes down its ongoing tests will be
redistributed immediately to other nodes
try free at rave and DB net so you
briefly mentioned a few key meetings
this is one of those things that happen
I'm always leery of because I've been in
a lot of useless meetings yeah how do
you how do you evaluate what a valuable
meeting looks like and you know not let
that kind of stuff snowball into you
half of my life is meetings yeah well
I'll talk a little bit about the
meetings that I love to see happen um
and then Laura actually has a lot of
great tips around how to you know
facilitate really high quality meetings
cuz you're right we're all in meetings
all the time as you grow and
responsibilities and kind of have bigger
and broader leadership roles you go from
being in no meetings to being constantly
in meetings and then you where do you
actually have time to do work to do the
creative thinking and the creative work
of building products and designing
products and leading teams so basically
what I like to do is make sure that in
the product development workflow there
are a few meetings that happen to make
sure everyone is aligned so at the start
of product development I think kickoffs
are really really valuable to get
everyone on the same page I opened them
up as broadly as possible to anyone in
the organization to come in and share
their point of view on a particular
customer problem what if they learned
what did they think are the the key
motivators and drivers for why customers
are having a hard time with XYZ and then
what I like to do is use some meetings
as the project moves into the design
phase when the product manager and the
designer you know really feel like they
have a strong point of view on what the
solution is and have found a good
solution that fits the problem
I like product reviews to make sure that
key stakeholders and leadership are
coming together to look at the problem
look at the solution and make sure it
all lines up really well
and another meeting that I love that I
actually don't think organizations do
enough is once something has shipped
whether it's two weeks later six weeks
later even six months later we grouping
and having leadership and stakeholders
and the team come together to look at
how the product is performing out there
look at the usage data
what anecdotal feedback have we gotten
from support what are people saying
about this and how are they actually
using it and look through that
qualitative and quantitative usage
information to decide what to do next so
those are some of the meetings I like to
see but for how to run good meetings I
think Laura has some really good
thoughts there thank you for the C I
love talking about meetings I totally
feel you you know like meetings if
you're in too many it can feel like oh
why do I have to have all of these
meetings but the first thing I like to
say is there's that old adage like this
could have been an email and actually a
bunch of studies have shown that usually
it can't be an email humans are so bad
at understanding context at
understanding tone and understanding
just you know normal human things that
you get from using your mouth words so I
use like to recommend the leaders and
specifically I hear this refrain often
from engineers which I just think is so
unfortunate like be better folks
understand that no this couldn't have
just been an email because often
important context is going to be lost or
important tone it's going to be lost if
we just haven't an email okay so how to
make a great meeting there's a bunch of
stuff that's been written out there on
how to make a great meeting I recommend
the people who are annoyed by meetings
go and read this they can figure out how
to suggest improvements or give feedback
on the meetings that they absolutely
loathe and despise but the first thing I
recommend is to separate the meeting
facilitation and the meeting leading
responsibility is being meaning this
person who's leading a meeting usually
also can't facilitate it like they're
using their brain power on making sure
that you know we're accomplishing the
goals of the meeting or they are really
heavily bought into whatever the content
is of the meeting which means they
probably can't also spend their
brainpower making sure that everybody is
being treated fairly and has equal
access to participate or is reading the
room for confused faces or making
that we end on time so it can be really
helpful to distinguish between those two
roles and get yourself a meeting
facilitator that way you can actually
focus on leading that meeting and
leading that group of people so a
facilitator I usually like to say should
be thinking about again fairness it does
everybody have equal access to
participate in this does everybody have
what they need to actually attend this
meeting is the is the enough context
been shared beforehand do we know what
the agenda is do we know what we're
trying to accomplish is that person who
is facilitating the meeting also
deputized with stopping steamrollers
from talking because that can be a
really tough power dynamic if that
facilitator isn't actually a strong
facilitator of steamrollers so yeah that
facilitation role is so so so critical
and one that I think often gets lost but
actually can be the difference between a
really powerful meeting and which stuff
gets done things are decided and people
can go back to their days and meetings
that just feel completely useless yeah
the last thing I'll say about this too
is try to distinguish between what work
can happen asynchronously outside of a
meeting and what work can be I could
happen synchronously inside of a meeting
meaning inside of a meeting it's really
helpful to make decisions to unblock
people to share again that really
important context and you got to think
about a meeting is like unlocking people
to go back into the next week of works
that they can do a ton of stuff they can
gather feedback they can gather
additional information they can go and
work on whatever it is that you decided
on in that meeting and then regroup
again if the phone we can say all right
let's make the next round of decisions
and unlock people to go again at that
asynchronous way of working again and so
do you have a sense of what what a
healthy level verbs let's say you're an
individual contributor right well it's
kind of a portion of your week to carve
off for useful meetings I don't know if
that calculus exists it's if that's a
little tricky especially as more and
more companies have distributed teams
are fully distributed I think that the
better way of thinking about it is as an
individual contributor are you getting
the information that you need to do your
job and are you able to provide the
information that you need in order to do
your job and and help your team be
successful
and if the answer to either of those
questions is no then look at the
communication flow and it could be that
what should be written down isn't being
written down like those living documents
it could be that the venue's in the
forums by which to as Laura said use
your mouth words and really digest
topics and more detail isn't happening
and so start like reverse engineering
from there for example I like you know
when we do research sprints I'm really
into continual short research Sprint's
yes you could write an awesome research
report and post it up on your wiki and
people can really learn from that but
the real actionable insights that come
out of user research and other research
tactics like surveys and stuff come when
you discuss that and it doesn't
necessarily have to be a meeting how can
you maybe discuss the results via
Basecamp ER or tools like that so I
would say start diagnosing where it
feels like communication is congested or
or blocked and then reverse engineer
from there whether you're missing
certain meetings or certain venues by
which folks can share their thoughts
synchronously or asynchronously the
other thing I want to add to this to the
kind of comes back to Travis's question
is like a manager should be setting
expectations for their individual
teammates what they should be expecting
in their in their given week to actually
attend meetings and be invested in
meetings because everybody's going to be
so different we were recently working
with an organization that was revamping
their recruiting process and as I was
gathering information from engineering
managers and from engineers about what
their current frustrations were with the
existing recruiting process I found a
lot of people were like it just takes
over my week and I don't know how to do
work around this and I'm not even sure
is this the right amount of time I
should be spending in interviews or
doing phone screens or reviewing
homework and so one of the things that
we did was establish like if you if your
team is hiring here's our estimated
amount of hours per week you're gonna be
spending either in interviews or in pre
Huddle's or in debrief after the
interview or phones we know whatever
else and just to set a little bit of
more of an expectation that was like
your home week is gonna be dominated by
hiring stuff and that's okay look we
have this new expectation
you know it helps product managers and
engineering managers and tech leads
estimate work better once you kind of
have some of those little expectations
so it really is on a manager to set
those expectations for their individual
teammates as much as possible I was kind
of hoping you had a number like 12 I
suppose that's why it's yeah that's
right I I haven't I've yet to mention
this on this podcast but there's been a
couple of topics that have come up so
far that ever reminded me of this study
about herb surgeons and so I guess heart
surgeons I don't know I'm not a surgeon
but I guess heart surgeons actually go
and do rotations at different hospitals
I'm not actually sure why I forget that
part of the study but the whole deal was
like you've got a home based hospital
and then you also do rotations maybe
it's like emergency rooms or something
else I can't remember but the point is
you have a home home hospital and then
you go around and do other heart heart
surgeries too and the study was trying
to figure out do you become more of an
expert the more surgeries you do it was
a study about expertise and they found
that you know you would assume the more
the more experienced you get the better
you become the higher success rate you
have with these surgeries actually they
found that although these doctors did
get better they only got better at their
home hospitals meaning they continued to
go around and the surgeries but
statistically it was with their home
team they you actually saw the benefits
of their expertise grow over time so
there's something in here I get that
this it doesn't exactly relate to me but
there's something in here about like
you've got to be with your home team and
you can only be better with your home
team and then you've gotta meet with
these people and understand these people
and like hang out with these people and
let get to know and share expectations
with these people and there's just so
much about this that like sure you can
go as an engineer and do work and work
siloed on projects or work with new
teams you know rotate on and off
different squads but actually what's
most critical your success and your team
success in the project success in the
company's success is like developing
those relationships with those people
around you developing that connective
tissue together empowered yeah one of
the things I've heard you talk about
previously is this idea of leading
difficult conversations it was a really
great tact what what is a difficult
conversation
I could talk all day about like our jobs
it's just a series of difficult
conversation so okay so difficult
conversations what I think about
difficult conversations I think about
someone who's in the leadership position
usually not always but usually neat
knows they need to have a talk with
somebody else that could be a
performance conversation that could be
hey we are organizing layoffs that could
be we need to completely throw out all
of his work that you've been doing for
the last two years because now we've got
a new company direction you know
difficulty you know comes in all forms
so when I think about this I often think
about clarity of message and how
important it is to get that right up
front I think about how you can like
develop empathy with this other person
so often when we need to communicate new
information that's gonna be hard for
someone to hear we have we know what it
feels like in our own bodies and heads
but we can't empathize with this other
person so remembering everybody else has
an amygdala everybody isn't it Magdalene
and our module is are responsible for
the fight-or-flight responses and
they're all they're doing is they're
they're taking in information from
outside and they are categorizing it as
either threat or reward and if a threat
feels threatening enough or module we'll
tell our prefrontal cortex that super
logical super rational complex
problem-solving part of our brain to go
on standby which means you're all you're
left is with like and it may be live in
human in front of you so as you're
getting ready to have that difficult
conversation think about the six core
needs that humans have at work that our
amygdala is is thinking about and is
just trying to secure for us so I talked
about these a little bit before but it's
belonging we need to feel like we belong
to this larger group of people we
understand how we relate to them the
image I usually like to show here is an
image of a group of ring-tailed lemurs
that sleep in super adorable group hug
naps for safety and warmth and so we
need to have a sense of belonging with
the crew the next one is a quality or
fairness so we all want to believe that
you know things are fair people are
being treated fairly people have access
to the same things and a fair way we all
know
if humans perceive a lack of fairness
will literally take to the streets about
it this is when you see usership decline
again riots happen so equality and
fairness and sense of improvement or
progress is really important we want to
feel that like we are growing or like
our company is growing or our team is
you know making making progress towards
a deadline are really important shift
date we all want to have a sense of
choice you know this is autonomy we
don't have too much choice I don't want
to just most of us don't want to have
like a Wild West out there although some
people do thrive in that scenario but we
have to have some balance of like choice
in front of us and what we can do every
day predictability is another big one we
want to feel like it's not just constant
waves of change again some people thrive
in that but most of us need a balance of
certainty and unpredictability and the
last one is status so we really want to
feel like we understand our place in the
hierarchy and that we're continuing
usually continuing to grow or at least
that like that doesn't feel threatened
so those I did them out of order but the
acronym for those is biceps which was
licensed as Creative Commons by Paula
Medina if you're familiar with scarf
models that's it's like scarf but a
little bit better because it's open
source and also has the improvement
progress one so difficult conversations
beep you're you've got to constantly be
on the lookout for potential threats to
this person's amygdala and so you can
you know take care to make sure that you
are helping them understand how this
affects their sense of belonging our
sense of certainty or sense of you know
equality and fairness or sense of
improvement in progress towards that
goal and that's usually the framing that
I like to give to people as they're
getting ready ramping up for that
difficult conversation so what TV tips
for people who have to deliver a
negative feedback I mean I think we all
we've heard sort of like the compliment
sandwich is that is that still the state
of the art or have we are there others
you know it's funny I actually I am I
was speaking at a conference recently
and they had a little prep for speakers
that was like a code of conduct prep but
also just look generally helpful like
getting to know you think before the
conference started and the person who
was leading it
she she's incredible and she actually
she was like I want to defend the
compliment sandwich because sometimes
again amygdalas we can
need dopamine hit like that hit dopamine
exactly
so I'll take back most of what I said
about compliment sandwiches I don't
think the compliment sandwiches are good
if you're trying to hide bad feedback if
you're trying to like couch it and other
things that's not good but she actually
called it a compliment
which I really liked but the idea here
is that like you shouldn't just be like
sandwiching negative feedback in between
two compliments in a way to like skirt
the issue I don't really like to frame
feedback in terms of adversity I'm sorry
observation and then impact and then a
request or a question so the observation
I talked about this a little bit a
minute ago of a behavior is like you
know something that can be recorded on a
video camera it's the who what when
where why it should be really obvious
really fact-based nothing based on your
assumptions the example I used like to
give is a someone has been sending me
emails that only have three to five
words in the body and it seems like
they're being just angry all the time
and they're being really short with me
and maybe it seems like they're mad at
me the observation I have for them if
I'm delivering feedback to them about
this can't be it seems like you're mad
all the time or your emails are really
short right that's those are judgments
those are assumptions those are not
observations an observation is routinely
on average your emails contain three to
five words in the body you know I have
observed this to be true and then you
kind of couple that with the impact at
that behavior and this is kind of where
you get to start to insert some of your
assumptions or judgments or just just
how it makes you feel so in the case of
the email I would say you know sometimes
I am I wonder if you're mad at me when I
received these emails with three to five
words in the body or I could say often
when you send me these emails that have
three to five words in the body I have
to respond and ask more clarifying
questions because I don't fully
understand what you mean off the bat and
the impact of that is that actually adds
time before I can actually go and do
this thing you know just as time to the
process overall which drags things down
so that's that's the impact usually I
like to ask and what's the impact of
that and then was the impact of that
anytime I'm coaching someone through
creating feedback because often there is
like a nugget that's really deep at the
end of this impact you know layer cake
that's really helpful for the other
person to understand
what's the impact of their behavior and
then you you cap it all off with a
request for them to change their
behavior or a question
requests are handy when you have a very
obvious thing that they can do
differently but honestly doesn't help
people grow and learn usually so I like
to encourage people to ask a question
instead and not like a loaded question
like why do you seem so mad all the time
that's my question it's gonna be helpful
but a question like can you help me
understand why you choose to write
emails with 3 to 5 words in the body or
what are what were you hoping to
accomplish with this email or what were
you hoping I would glean from this email
coaching questions like that that start
with what that are open-ended tend to
help this other person start to think
about their behavior and the impact that
it's having and then start to form their
own solution to this problem because
you've equipped them with knowing what
the impact is you don't have to look
spell it out for them how to correct it
like they can come through their own
conclusions about it and usually the
people's amygdalas are so much more open
and receptive to this form of feedback
because again it doesn't feel
threatening you're not making passing
judgment you're not making assumptions
all you're doing is saying here are the
facts on the ground of the observation
and the impact what can we do about this
together it's it's again so so so handy
when you need to have those difficult
conversations with feedback I are just
gonna say that this feedback equation
like when Laura first explained it to me
it's so simple it's so succinct and it's
so powerful because 99% of leading is
giving critical feedback having
difficult conversations right generally
you're stoked when you get to celebrate
things and things are going great but
often times you do have to have those
difficult conversations and so often
managers and leaders aren't in any way
given the skills to do that properly and
so then they can shirk it it can it can
make them nervous it can make them
almost dread their job and their role
but if they're just given a little bit
of tactical advice on how to do it in
such a clear and valuable way it can be
so free it can you can start embracing
having those conversations and then
reaping the benefit of having those
difficult conversations things get
better things get shared more openly you
know you get the feelings out I have
inherited so
many engineers in the course of my
management career they just never got
any feedback and so I'd inherit them and
I would often hear from their previous
manager like oh they're terrible this
thing oh they're not really a team
player
oh whatever and I usually asked like
cool when was the last time you gave
them this feedback like yeah and so that
you know whenever I start to observe the
same behavior and I share that feedback
usually what happens is these people are
like what really like I had no idea that
this was that people were preceding me
this way or that this was the impact of
that behavior and I'm like right but
these poor individuals were never
equipped with the feedback its feedback
is a gift you're giving us someone else
it doesn't I get it it's scary it feels
hard it feels weird to deliver feedback
but like genuinely it would make
everybody's life so much easier if we
were better every team Lee giving
constructive feedback I feel like there
can be this tricky balance between the
idea of you know delivering hard news
and keeping your team motivated you know
that's sort of one of the things that I
as a manager certainly think about how
what do you think the right way to do
that is oh man right it's so it's so
hard I am deep and I are actually
working on a book right now about all
the stuff that we're talking about on
this podcast and just yesterday I sent
to our editor on to Tippa the chapter on
communication and communication often
for us as leaders means like doing that
tricky balance like creating clarity
also sharing honest hard updates and
Austin still trying to motivate people
so usually what I've seen organizations
do this really well it's because
everybody has this shared understanding
of where we're trying to go as an
organization like what is our North Star
what is the thing that we're aiming for
which means that when you hear hard news
everybody around the company is able to
understand how this impacts our North
Star how this impacts them and whether
or not makes sense towards this North
Star when I see organizations fall apart
at the seams it's because it's change
has happened and it doesn't make sense
in the context of that North Star like
where were we trying to go on this
mission why on earth is this new thing
why were we acquired why do we have
layoffs why do you know whatever the
thing is it's because people can't
reason about whatever this thing is so
usually when I think about big hard
scary you know the CEO is changing over
or again acquiring happens or you know
whatever it is I think about how can I
help people see how this relates to our
organizations North Star where we're
trying to go and how does that it makes
that she back go from being such a
personal thing to being part of a
broader context so it's a little more
palatable it's a little more
understanding why it's even being called
out it's not because you you know John
have done something poorly it's like
okay John this thing that you're doing
has this halo effect that's like maybe
holding us back and so we want to help
you get into a better place for the
benefit of you the team and the broader
mission sounds like context is is pretty
key to bringing it to communication so
how can you give some examples of what
that looks like done well oh yeah well I
mean Laura and I learned this together
when we were leading teams at
Kickstarter you know one of the things
that we did to give context and to give
context often and in a unified and
consistent manner was that we would
share communication updates together and
I mean that literally like we would
stand up there together to co-lead All
Hands meetings with the entire product
design data and engineering teams we
would co-author emails together like
signed by both of us to announce
strategic changes or staffing changes or
anything like that so you know one of
the ways to give context is to
communicate often to communicate
consistently you want all of your
leadership to be sort of you know
banging on the same drum together and
making sure you're kind of working in
lockstep that's how that adage you know
a rising tide lifts all boats it's
because that's sort of happening
together so we did a lot of things where
we would communicate together and avoid
giving disjointed communications or
communicating in a siloed manner and so
we do that by leading across
organizational meetings or writing
cross-organizational emails or opening
across organizational office hours and
so when our team saw us kind of
coordinating together and getting that
shared contact so it wasn't just me
giving an update to the product and
design team Laura give me an update
Sharon team but us
giving an update together tying it all
together what it means
cross-functionally in the broader
mission and how that translates down to
specific functional teams that was
really really helpful so it finally
meant that people started understanding
the why behind the things that we were
asking for hey look we got to pull the
ship data up on this critical project or
hey we decided to to defer this project
that everyone was really excited about
because of X Y Z even they got that
context it made those kinds of changes
less scary less concerning and more like
oh okay I get it
great thanks for sharing with me the
path to that decision so many times
leaders don't share the reasoning behind
their decisions the path that took them
there the other options that they may be
discarded along the way to making that
decision you've got to share that
backstory share that journey to the
decision because that buy-in then comes
when people understand that that process
that brought you there because otherwise
it's just lopsided information you know
like just your trusted advisors will
understand how you got there so that
actually the other thing that we did was
whenever there was something that only
affected one subset of teams deep and I
would still share talking points with
each other and with our you know the
leaders in our organizations that way
everybody still had the context if I had
talking points for my engineering
managers about an engineering management
thing I would still share it with deep
and I would still share it with their
product managers because it was so
critical for us all to have that
occasion because we had these honest
candid conversations our team started
having more honest and candid
conversations with each other in
explaining explaining the path to their
decision so I mean literally I started
seeing in our product and design reviews
more explanation around discarded design
choices and the way that someone sort of
landed upon the solution that they were
presenting and so because we were really
good about sharing the the pathway the
narrative the history to a decision the
team started mimicking that behavior
which was really good and and helped
improve accountability and and Trust
awesome well look is there any sort of
additional advice for managers who are
looking for ways to be better leaders or
grow their team's you think is important
to call out get yourself a crew of
people who are there to support
you you know people who have more
experience than you do have less
experience than you you do because as
fresh eyes are really helpful get you
know lean on people who are in other
industries one of my best mentors was a
is a CFO you know it was really handy to
have her in my corner find people who
will sponsor you who will put your name
in the ring for things fine to find
yourself a coach I mean this is gonna
sound selfish I'm a coach but like find
yourself a coach because getting that
the other person to just be a champion
for you that you know you can unload on
and share your your truth with and
honest have someone else just kind of
reflect back for you and help you
introspect and find your own path to
things could be so so so valuable I like
to call it my manager Voltron because
it's like all of these different
individual managers are coming together
to make up this one amazing unicorn so
let me ask one follow on to that how I
know this is gonna sound kind of
ridiculous how do you ask for that like
what is the what's the structure is it
hey hey let's just have a meeting every
couple weeks if you find a good mentor
what's a good cadence for getting input
from from strong people or yeah so I I
usually advise against walking into
someone's office and saying hello could
you please be a mentor or a sponsor for
me because that's not actionable that's
all that helpful so a vet Pasqua who's
the CTO at Meetup
she told me about one of the things that
she she does and actually I realized
that she did this to me which is how we
got first connected is she'll she'll
come up with a topic that's genuinely of
interest to her at the time it was she
was reorganizing her infrastructure
organization and so she reached out to
me a Canberra email or Twitter or
something to be like hey I am planning
on you know Rio arguing my in for a team
I I know that you run an infra team
would you be game for talking about it
over coffee I mean she knew me enough to
know that that was something I would
probably be interested in talking about
and sharing my experience and people
love talking about them so loosely
that's her way of beginning to develop
those relationships she'll find
something that we have in common that
she genuinely has a you know a challenge
she's trying to overcome or something
that she wants to find out
about she'll ask people to coffee about
that and that's how she begins these
relationships because over time you
hopefully on each other I usually
recommend you know not being a jerk
being someone who other people will want
to vouch for who you know people will
want to help you because often in those
relationships people are putting their
reputation on the line for you whether
or not it's something huge like trying
to hire you for a job even if it's
something like introducing you to their
network they want to know that you're
not gonna be you know a total jerk
about it yeah doing good work Jenny only
being helpful to them to I even if I
can't actually help in people's
day-to-day I try to offer to give them
space to vent or be a rubber duck you
know help them workshop an idea or think
through a new solution even those tiny
things can be a value to them too
I recommend you know Twitter is kind of
a tire fire these days but that has
historically been where I've gotten to
know people going to local meetups
there's so many groups in so many areas
there's some thriving different CTO
clubs in New York that I've met some
folks at just kind of like developing
those connections and and trying to find
that place of genuinely you could use a
help on this very specific thing and ask
someone else for help on that it's but
very specific thing is usually because
it has to be like co-located can you
kind of create your manager voltron
remotely like maybe reach out to people
who you know through Twitter or know
through your extended network to be like
let's chat regularly let's let's create
that that forum where we can learn and
share from each other yeah I'll be
honest most of my manager voltron is
over video probably only a couple of
them do I see in person right girly and
here's a secret it stresses me out
to have setup routine like coffees
people because I'm like oh it just takes
so much time out of my I have to commute
to where but that thing isn't just like
being at home but but video or phone
calls honestly can be so easy for me
especially when it feels like I can
reach out to someone to talk about
something that feels pressing for me or
that they can reach out when they want
to talk about something feels pressing
for them rather than having a there's
very few deep and I have a biweekly
one-on-one phone call yeah but we also
feel like we can cancel it whenever we
don't either
you know it's
right there's no expectation there and I
think that's that's so life safety it's
critical because I think I would just be
stressed out and annoyed by it if I you
know especially with the multitude of
people who are asking me to go to coffee
or to have routine chats I'm like no
just tell me when you want something
that help and I will be there well deep
and Lara thanks for joining us today
this is Travis can we offer software
engineering radio and we'll talk to you
next time thanks for having us Thanks
digital ocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size we're moving
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software that customers love
with thousands of in-depth tutorials in
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digital ocean for free by
getting a 100 dollar infrastructure
credit at doco /sc radio thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at SE - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio slack calm you can
also email us a team at SC - radio net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening